<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://cwarrendale.com/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
C Warren Dale
</title>
<link>
http://cwarrendale.com/
</link>
<description>
The personal blog of an opinionated and artistically-inclined technologist
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Sat, 19 Mar 2016 17:08:27 -0500
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
http://cwarrendale.com/posts-output/was_roger_right_i_spit_on_your_grave.html
</guid>
<link>
http://cwarrendale.com/posts-output/was_roger_right_i_spit_on_your_grave.html
</link>
<title>
Was Roger Right: I Spit On Your Grave (1978)
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;content warning: rape, graphic violence, and spoilers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;&lt;strong&gt;was&amp;#95;roger&amp;#95;right&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#95;about&amp;#95;&lt;em&gt;i&amp;#95;spit&amp;#95;on&amp;#95;your&amp;#95;grave&lt;/em&gt;?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was Roger Right&lt;/strong&gt; about &lt;em&gt;I Spit On Your Grave&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/i-spit-on-your-grave-1980'&gt;Oh heavens no&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A vile bag of garbage named &quot;I Spit on Your Grave&quot; is playing in Chicago theaters this week. It is a movie so sick, reprehensible and contemptible that I can hardly believe it's playing in respectable theaters, such as Plitt's United Artists. But it is. Attending it was one of the most depressing experiences of, my life [&lt;em&gt;sic&lt;/em&gt;]. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/07/ISpitOnYourGraveposter.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href='http://amzn.to/1VjpvcY'&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Spit On Your Grave&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a pretty legendary film, as far as grindhouse goes. I don't even remember the first time I heard of it because I've known about it forever. It was such a cultural force it founded the genre of &quot;rape/revenge&quot; films, and with that you also have a pretty clear idea of the plot: a woman is raped, and she gets revenge. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say that the movie is obviously good because it is well-known or influential. In fact, I went into this movie expecting bog-standard low-budget exploitation fare, with a reputation built entirely on shock value—and I am not easily shocked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This movie surprised me. It was good in ways best described by negating every part of the following excerpt from Roger's review: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a film without a shred of artistic distinction. It lacks even simple craftsmanship. There is no possible motive for exhibiting it, other than the totally cynical hope that it might make money. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, it is craftsmanship and craftsmanship alone that redeems this movie. In this post-&lt;em&gt;Grave&lt;/em&gt; world there are rape/revenge movies that aren't worth the bits they take up on &lt;a href='http://www.millcreekent.com/'&gt;Mill Creek Entertaiment&lt;/a&gt;'s hard drives. It is not culturally important to simply show rapists getting murdered. What sets &lt;em&gt;Grave&lt;/em&gt; apart is that the filmmakers really believed they were making a motion picture. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For instance, if the film only meant to show a graphic rape followed by graphic violence with the thinnest veneer of justification, you'd think it might not spend half an hour setting up the characters before the rape happens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, if the film was made entirely without craft or art, you might think that this half-hour of set-up was boring or pointless, but it was not. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The story of &quot;I Spit on Your Grave&quot; is told with moronic simplicity. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no attempt to develop the personalities of the characters - they are, simply, a girl and four men, one of them mentally retarded. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are two seemingly contradictary responses to this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;That's wrong. There are several character-building moments through the entire narrative.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's true that the characters are not fleshed out &lt;em&gt;in detail&lt;/em&gt;, but this is thematically important.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's deal with these one at a time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;the&amp;#95;characters&amp;#95;are&amp;#95;not&amp;#95;blank&amp;#95;slates&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Characters Are Not Blank Slates&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The characters are not facile stock clichés, either. The heroine runs the biggest risk of this—she's a city writer visiting the country so she can focus on a novel she's writing that is clearly just about herself. You know, the default Stephen King protagonist, and also Stephen King. The relationship between the four men is complicated, even beyond the obvious factor of the mentally handicapped Matthew.  Even the ringleader Johnny's clueless wife, who only appears in two scenes, shows more character than Ebert's charge suggests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My favorite moment of character building appears in a scene in which the four men sit in the local diner two weeks after the rape. Stanley blurts out details of the crime loudly enough to be overheard, and Johnny hits him and scolds him. Stanley feels guilty and is visibly hurt by Johnny's outburst. Johnny, a man who orchestrated the rape and, he believes, murder of a woman and feels no ounce of remose, &lt;em&gt;feels guilty that he has upset his friend&lt;/em&gt;, and tries to coax a smile out of him&lt;label for=&quot;sn-ladykiller&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt; &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-ladykiller&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;/&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;He says one of Stan's &quot;classic Ladykiller smiles.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;. I found this terrifying, and so should you. Perhaps Roger did too, but forgot that that was the point of the film.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;the&amp;#95;characters&amp;#95;are&amp;#95;supposed&amp;#95;to&amp;#95;be&amp;#95;vague&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Characters Are Supposed to Be Vague&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The film &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; supposed to be terrifying, by the way. Not from shock value or jump scares, but from plausibility. This is why the characterization is so subtle: the characters in this movie could be &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Jennifer Hills pulls into the gas station when she gets to the town where she has rented her summer home, the conversation she has with the gas station attendant is so benign and bereft of the grim foreboding so beloeved of cabin-in-the-woods-style exploitation that my earlier suspicions she was already talking to her would-be rapist were put to rest. It was only when the film returned to his character multiple times without introducing any others I realized this guy really was capable of the atrocity for which this film is famous.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, Jennifer lures Johnny out into woods where he raped her, and forces him to strip at gunpoint. She is about to put him down execution-style when he tries to justify his actions by referring to their first interaction, giving classic lines about leading him on with her scanty dress and coquettish behavior. We've all heard these arguments before, of course—and Jennifer is so appalled she decides he deserves a more personalized death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The message is clear: rape can happen to anyone, and anyone can commit rape. The entire film is structured around this idea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[There is] an unbelievably grotesque and inappropriate scene in which she enters a church and asks forgiveness for the murders she plans to commit. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This scene is kind of unnecessary, and the lone organist playing to an empty church makes it surreal-borderline-silly, but I did not find it grotesque or inappropriate, least of all unbelievably so. Perhaps this is because I lack religious feeling, but &lt;a href='http://www.rogerebert.com/rogers-journal/how-i-believe-in-god'&gt;Roger was not exactly brimming with it himself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;How did the audience react to all of this? Those who were vocal seemed to be eating it up. The middle-aged, white-haired man two seats down from me, for example, talked aloud, After the first rape: &quot;That was a good one!&quot; After the second: &quot;That'll show her!&quot; After the third: &quot;I've seen some good ones, but this is the best.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is indefensible. I am appalled—though not surprised—that anybody reacted this way to this film and I am happy to report that the crowd I saw it with reacted with due solemnity—which is to say, not at all. I cannot say if my feelings on the film would have been colored by such an environment, nor do I wish to insult Roger by claiming he could have had his artistic judgment so easily clouded, but such an experience would certainly have left a rotten taste in my mouth not easily forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;in&amp;#95;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Score&lt;/strong&gt;: 4/5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roger's Score&lt;/strong&gt;: Thumb's Down. (Not even a star rating!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was Roger Right?&lt;/strong&gt; No, and neither was anyone he saw it with. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Fri, 18 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://cwarrendale.com/posts-output/2016-03-10-was-roger-right-whats-up-doc-1972.html
</guid>
<link>
http://cwarrendale.com/posts-output/2016-03-10-was-roger-right-whats-up-doc-1972.html
</link>
<title>
Was Roger Right: What's Up, Doc? (1972)
</title>
<description>
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I love Roger Ebert. I don't know enough about film criticism for it to mean anything to say that he is my favorite film critic, but it stands nonetheless. He is sometimes criticized for being too soft on movies, for &quot;liking everything.&quot; Well, a few responses:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&quot;Liking everything&quot; is pretty weak, as far as supposed flaws go. The Dalai Lama &quot;likes everything&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;a href='http://amzn.to/21lJya6'&gt;definitely&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href='http://amzn.to/21lJyHd'&gt;not&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href='http://amzn.to/1UjY1TN'&gt;true&lt;/a&gt; about Roger Ebert.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; true is that Roger always &lt;em&gt;tried&lt;/em&gt; to find something to like in every movie he saw; he would judge the movie on its own terms and report honestly on how he though it measured. He usually could find something to like and he was usually right.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usually.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But not always.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what I would like to explore in a series of film reviews is whether I agree with Roger's review of some movie I've recently seen and felt strongly about. I don't always mean to find movies we disagree on, but I also will try to emphasize where he and I differ. Anyway, without further ado I present the first installment:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;&lt;strong&gt;was&amp;#95;roger&amp;#95;right&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#95;about&amp;#95;'&lt;em&gt;what's&amp;#95;up,&amp;#95;doc?&lt;/em&gt;'&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was Roger Right&lt;/strong&gt; about '&lt;em&gt;What's Up, Doc?&lt;/em&gt;'&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://image.tmdb.org/t/p/w396/x1rkdx7qQKC8lTqlM7EwkmDSXd8.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;What's Up, Doc?&lt;/em&gt; (1972), Directed by Peter Bogdanovich. Starring Barbra Streisand and Ryan O'Neal&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;a href='http://amzn.to/1QLvFjY'&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's Up, Doc?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is film school brat Peter Bogdanovich's second film, the (superficially) less ambitious follow-up to his seminal directorial debut, &lt;em&gt;The Last Picture Show&lt;/em&gt;. Both films are (as would prove to be the hallmark of Bogdanovich's whole career) steeped in nostalgia - and deep knowledge of - classical Hollywood cinema. I've never seen &lt;em&gt;The Last Picture Show&lt;/em&gt; - just &lt;em&gt;Paper Moon&lt;/em&gt;, before this - but this film demonstrates a familiarity with golden-era Hollywood comedy that rivals Mel Brooks at his best (i.e. &lt;em&gt;Young Franktenstein&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was extremely taken with this film. Billed as a romantic comedy, it delivers on both promises: it is terribly funny - sometimes extremely clever, sometimes rauckus, sometimes wacky, but only rarely stale or predictable; and it is a sweet love story.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal to be said on this second aspect. It is, I think, pretty well understood that romantic comedies with female protagonists are structurally different from those with male protagonists. When a woman stars, she generally has to juggle the affections of multiple suitors and eventually choose between them; when a man stars, he usually has to persist in courting a reluctant woman. I've always thought it would be fun to try a male-structured comedy with a female star, and in fact that is just what this movie is. It's actually quite interesting: it has so much in common with '30s and '40s studio pictures, but its plot is the fundamentally modern story of a woman who &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; to be with a man - and gets him!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barbra Streisand really does steal the show in that regard. It takes a remarkably charming woman to make us forget (or forgive) that she is trying to sabotage Ryan O'Neal's (admittedly sham of an) engagement - but she does it and then some. The audience is rooting for Streisand's character from the very beginning. She is captivating in every scene, which seems to justify the havoc that she causes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I said earlier this was &lt;em&gt;superficially&lt;/em&gt; less ambitious, because although it is, as Ebert notes, a &quot;screwball comedy utterly lacking in redeeming social importance,&quot; it demanded a meticulous attention to detail - something that comes through in the camera work, the set design, the screenplay, and the wardrobe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But enough about me. &lt;a href='http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/whats-up-doc-1972'&gt;What does Roger think&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;[Bogdanovich] directs with the slapdash economy of the 1930s comedies. &quot;What's Up, Doc?&quot; is only about 90 minutes long, takes no time for sloppy romantic scenes, and remembers to be funny even when Miss Streisand is singing (she reclines on top of the piano, natch). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I disagree somewhat here - although the piano scene is somewhat funny, it is also nonsensical, sloppy, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; romantic (they sing &quot;As Time Goes By&quot;, which gets me every time). However, overall he is right about the sense of economy - I am shocked to learn that the movie was only 90 minutes. It felt far more substantial.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt; [Streisand] proves herself as our most accomplished screen comedienne. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is bonkers. Streisand's character is charismatic, quirky, and alluring, but a laff riot she is not. Not only does the early '70s have enough funny leading ladies to go around - on TV, Mary Tyler Moore, Lily Tomlin, and Carol Burnett for starters - but you don't have to look any further than this film to find a comic genius. &lt;em&gt;What's Up, Doc?&lt;/em&gt; is actually the big-screen debut of Madeline Kahn (remember, &lt;em&gt;Young Frankenstein&lt;/em&gt;?). She plays O'Neal's demanding and ambitious fiancee, and if Streisand's character is the more lovable, Kahn's is the juicier role.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt; The chase scene (Barbra and Ryan aboard a grocery delivery wagon inside a Chinese dragon, being chased downhill by three cars) is as nice as anything in this line in a long time. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is true - and, indeed, for a long time to come. This chase scene goes unmatched until at &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; 1980's &lt;em&gt;The Blues Brothers&lt;/em&gt;, and several times during this extended climax I thought it had even that famous sequence bested.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It seems I did not choose a good Ebert review for my first installment - he had little to say about the film at all, let alone something to agree with or not. But we soldier on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;in&amp;#95;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Score&lt;/strong&gt;: 5/5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roger's Score&lt;/strong&gt;: 3/4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was Roger Right?&lt;/strong&gt; He liked the movie, but his review is short and he never revisited in any of his &lt;em&gt;Great Movies&lt;/em&gt; books. I don't think he liked it &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt;, although I suspect if he knew how few movies Bogdanovich was going to come out with he would have paid it a little more mind.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Thu, 10 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600
</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://cwarrendale.com/posts-output/2016-03-08-getting-started-with-lambdanative.html
</guid>
<link>
http://cwarrendale.com/posts-output/2016-03-08-getting-started-with-lambdanative.html
</link>
<title>
Let's Learn Together: LambdaNative, Part 1
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt; 	&lt;blockquote&gt; 	MARGE: But I could... give piano lessons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;	LISA: But you don't play the piano.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;	MARGE: I just got to stay one lesson ahead of the kid.	 	&lt;footer&gt;The Simpsons, &lt;cite&gt;S14E12, &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://simpsons.wikia.com/wiki/I'm&amp;#95;Spelling&amp;#95;as&amp;#95;Fast&amp;#95;as&amp;#95;I&amp;#95;Can&quot;&gt;I'm Spelling as Fast as I Can&lt;/a&gt;&quot;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt; 	&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;let's&amp;#95;learn&amp;#95;together&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Let's Learn Together&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am going to kick off my new blog with a new series of posts, called &lt;em&gt;Let's Learn Together&lt;/em&gt;. I suspect most &quot;Getting Started&quot; tutorials you see online are written more-or-less just after the author has learned how to start off themselves, but they have already learned from their beginners' mistakes and the finished posts make them look like fonts of wisdom. I am going to continue in this proud tradition, only I am going to keep in all of my mistakes, for your reading pleasure. &lt;strong&gt;Don't follow along with this &quot;tutorial&quot; as you read it, because you will certainly do unnecessary work. Read through the whole post to a get big-picture understanding of what to do - and what not to do!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being, as I have written, an &lt;em&gt;opinionated&lt;/em&gt; technologist, I choose my technology stack according to my preferences for development characteristics. I prefer functional programming to imperative (by a wide margin), and as such I haven't done much in the way of mobile development. I did aid in porting a native Java application to Android a few years back, but the experience was not ideal and it did not serve to entice me further down the path of native mobile development. The mere prospect of coding an entire project in the Android SDK or - shudder to think it - in Objective-C thrilled me, filled me with fantastic terrors never felt before. So I never pursued it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did work with PhoneGap on an iOS project, and in fact, as a front-end developer by day, I found the experience quite pleasant. I never returned to it, though, because I wouldn't &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; to work in JavaScript on a personal project; I wanted a cross-platform experience a little more suited to my idiosyncratic tastes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href='http://lambdanative.org'&gt;LambdaNative&lt;/a&gt;! LambdaNative is a cross-platform (mobile AND desktop) development environment written in Scheme, the language that, when I learned it freshman year of college, was my first breatheless introduction to the world of functional programming. Sounds great! Now, what to do with it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;the&amp;#95;project&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Project&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What mobile app should we make? A lame Twitter clone? Some worthless Bejeweled-style casual game? Uber for dogs? I think...&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I really like pool. In fact, I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; pool. My brother has a pool table, and although we play together as often as we can, he doesn't always have someone else to play with. Looking for decent skill-building solo games, we discovered &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowlliards'&gt;bowlliards&lt;/a&gt;. Bowling scoring is famously a little bit complicated, however, and we soon looked for automated ways of keeping score. Although several high-quality bowling score-keeping apps exist, they are all too focused on bowling. Existing apps in the bowlliards space are buggy, narrowly tailored to their platforms, and unmaintained. A vacuum exists, ready for a cross-platform, open-source solution!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;getting&amp;#95;started&amp;#95;with&amp;#95;lambdanative&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Getting Started with LambdaNative&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;LambdaNative has extensive documentation, but how to actually get the environment set up is not entirely clear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;first&amp;#95;attempt.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;First attempt.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;My first attempt at getting LambdaNative set up involved &lt;a href='https://github.com/part-cw/lambdanative'&gt;cloning the GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. Then I was sitting in the repo, looking at its contents. What now?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ ls
  apps	        docs	   libraries	  loaders   modules	      README.md	      targets    VERSION
  config.guess  fonts	   LICENSE	  Makefile  plugins	      scripts	      templates
  configure     languages  LNCONFIG.h.in  make.sh   PROFILE.template  SETUP.template  tools
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, this is the source repository. Probably you have to build the package if you want to use it to develop against. Let's try &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;ing the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ make
  Error: &amp;#126;/.lambdanative/config.cache: file does not exist
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hmm. Well, the &lt;a href='https://github.com/part-cw/lambdanative/wiki'&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt; says something about &quot;&lt;a href='https://github.com/part-cw/lambdanative/wiki/Compilation'&gt;Compilation&lt;/a&gt;&quot;, that sounds promising!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The configure command follows the format: &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;./configure &amp;lt;app&amp;gt; &amp;#91;android|ios|bb10|macosx|win32|linux|linux486|openbsd&amp;#93; &amp;#91;debug|release&amp;#93; &amp;#91;verbose&amp;#93;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt; &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;app&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is the name of the application, and must match a directory name in the &lt;code&gt;./apps&lt;/code&gt; framework subdirectory.	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, so this page is actually about compiling projects we make &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; LambdaNative. Fair enough, that will be useful later! But from here I see another page, about &quot;&lt;a href='https://github.com/part-cw/lambdanative/wiki/System-wide-installation'&gt;System-wide Installation&lt;/a&gt;&quot;. Let's have a look!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;second&amp;#95;attempt&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Second Attempt&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The LambdaNative package, obtained from &lt;a href='https://github.com/part-cw/lambdanative/releases'&gt;LambdaNative Releases&lt;/a&gt; should be placed in a system-wide location for third-party programs, such as &lt;code&gt;/usr/local&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;/opt&lt;/code&gt;. Next, the LambdaNative initialization script, located in scripts/lambdanative needs to be placed in system path, e.g. &lt;code&gt;/bin&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, the &lt;code&gt;LAMBDANATIVE=&lt;/code&gt; variable in this script needs to be overwritten with actual full LambdaNative path. The system is now ready for use. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, so the package is available in this release! Let's download one and see what we have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#42;downloads&amp;#42;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ tar xvf lambdanative-1.0.7.tar.gz
&amp;#91;lots of unzipping&amp;#93;
$ cd lambdanative-1.0.7/
$ ls
  apps	        docs	   libraries	  loaders   modules	      README.md	      targets    VERSION
  config.guess  fonts	   LICENSE  	  Makefile  plugins	      scripts	      templates
  configure     languages  LNCONFIG.h.in  make.sh   PROFILE.template  SETUP.template  tools
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hmm. That looks familiar. The major release isn't a build, it's just a canonical package of the source code. Again, this makes sense in retrospect! So now what? The Wiki insists that all I need to do is put the &quot;package&quot; in some globally-accessible directory and then I can use the scripts. Maybe they mean...the source repository? In &lt;code&gt;/opt&lt;/code&gt;? Well, let's give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;# cp lambdanative/scripts/lambdanative /usr/bin
# chmod +x /usr/bin/lambdanative
# mv lambdanative /opt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then we set &lt;code&gt;LAMBDANATIVE= /opt/lambdanative&lt;/code&gt; like the wiki says, and...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ lambdanative init
  lambdanative: line 5: /opt/lambdanative/: Is a directory
  ERROR: this script has not been configured.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, that's not it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;final&amp;#95;attempt&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Final Attempt&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Googling for solutions, I discovered that &lt;a href='https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/lambdanative/'&gt;LambdaNative is packed up in Arch Linux's &quot;Arch User Repository&quot;&lt;/a&gt;, and it's totally up-to-date. Luckily, I am an Arch Linux user! I install the package with yaourt and leave you to struggle along on your own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, now that the installation worked, let's see what &lt;code&gt;LAMBDANATIVE&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; refers to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ head /usr/bin/lambdanative
  #!/bin/sh
  # LambdaNative initialization script to be placed in system path

  # Override this with actual lambdanative location
  LAMBDANATIVE=/usr/share/lambdanative

  if &amp;#91; &amp;quot;X$LAMBDANATIVE&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;X&amp;quot; &amp;#93;; then
    echo &amp;quot;ERROR: this script has not been configured.&amp;quot;
    exit
  fi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's set to &lt;code&gt;/usr/share/lambdanative&lt;/code&gt;. Let's see what's that all about!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ ls /usr/share/lambdanative
  apps	        docs	   libraries	  Makefile  plugins	      scripts	      targets    VERSION
  config.guess  fonts  	   LNCONFIG.h.in  make.sh   PROFILE.template  SETUP	      templates
  configure     languages  loaders	  modules   README.md	      SETUP.template  tools
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;What! That IS the source repo after all. What went wrong???&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oops. When I tried editing the &lt;code&gt;lambdanative&lt;/code&gt; script, I put a space between the &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; and the path to lambdanative. So everything died, but instead of throwing a syntax error, it set &lt;code&gt;LAMBDANATIVE&lt;/code&gt; to nothing (hence the second error message) and tried to execute the directory (hence the first). I hate bash. Moving on.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;creating&amp;#95;the&amp;#95;foundation&amp;#95;of&amp;#95;our&amp;#95;application&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Creating the foundation of our application&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that that's set up, get ready to make our LambdaNative development directory. The environment is designed so all your LambdaNative projects are developed in the same directory tree, with their sources in the &lt;code&gt;lambdanative/apps&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;$ mkdir lambdanative
$ cd lambdanative
$ lambdanative init
$ lambdanative create bowlliards gui
$ ls
  apps	     Makefile  PROFILE
  configure  modules   README.md
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, check out the template source file, &lt;code&gt;apps/bowlliards/main.scm&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;scheme&quot;&gt;;; LambdaNative gui template

&amp;#40;define gui #f&amp;#41;

&amp;#40;main
;; initialization
  &amp;#40;lambda &amp;#40;w h&amp;#41;
    &amp;#40;make-window 320 480&amp;#41;
    &amp;#40;glgui-orientation-set! GUI&amp;#95;PORTRAIT&amp;#41;
    &amp;#40;set! gui &amp;#40;make-glgui&amp;#41;&amp;#41;

    ;; initialize gui here

  &amp;#41;
;; events
  &amp;#40;lambda &amp;#40;t x y&amp;#41; 
    &amp;#40;if &amp;#40;= t EVENT&amp;#95;KEYPRESS&amp;#41; &amp;#40;begin 
      &amp;#40;if &amp;#40;= x EVENT&amp;#95;KEYESCAPE&amp;#41; &amp;#40;terminate&amp;#41;&amp;#41;&amp;#41;&amp;#41;
    &amp;#40;glgui-event gui t x y&amp;#41;&amp;#41;
;; termination
  &amp;#40;lambda &amp;#40;&amp;#41; #t&amp;#41;
;; suspend
  &amp;#40;lambda &amp;#40;&amp;#41; &amp;#40;glgui-suspend&amp;#41; &amp;#40;terminate&amp;#41;&amp;#41;
;; resume
  &amp;#40;lambda &amp;#40;&amp;#41; &amp;#40;glgui-resume&amp;#41;&amp;#41;
&amp;#41;

;; eof
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a simple event-loop driven program that listens for key events and quits when you hit the Escape key. You can compile it right now and try it out! Next time, we'll learn - together! - how to create GUI controls.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<enclosure>

</enclosure>
<pubDate>
Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0600
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
